Friends,
各位朋友，
after so many years of hard work,
经过多年的努力，
we are finally listed.
我们终于被列入名录了。
Just kidding
开玩笑啦，Arashi Vision Inc. 的
It’s not me who is listed
创始人不是我。
The handsome guy next to me
我旁边这位帅哥
is the founder of IArashi Vision Inc., JK.
才是 Arashi Vision Inc. 的创始人，JK。
Don’t be fooled by his young age
不要被他的年轻年龄所迷惑，
he is a millennial
他是一位千禧一代，也是
he first milennial to be listed on
首位入选
the Science and Technology Innovation Board.
科学技术创新委员会的千禧一代。
As for me, although I am still a little far from being listed
至于我，虽然我离今天上市还有一段距离，但
today I want to take you to uncover the secrets
我希望带你们揭开
of what a company will go through when
一家公司想要
it wants to be listed on the
在
A-share market.
A股市场上市所要经历的种种秘密。
It is said that it is difficult to be listed on the A-share market
据说在A股市场上市很难，
and the threshold is high.
门槛很高。
Why is it so high?
为什么这么高？
What are the unknown ways behind it
这背后究竟隐藏着哪些未知的秘密？
Doesn’t it sound very mysterious and exciting?
听起来是不是很神秘，很刺激？
Let me tell you
我向几位
friends who specialize in A-share IPOs.
专门研究A股IPO的朋友咨询过。
Now my head is full of knowledge.
现在我脑子里装满了知识。
Let's pick out some suitable ones to talk about
让我们挑选一些合适的例子
in the video
在视频中讨论。
To go public,
要上市，
first of all, we have to have a larger business.
首先我们必须拥有更大的企业规模。
Let's say the revenue is 1 billion.
假设营收为10亿美元。
This step is very simple.
这一步非常简单。
Let's skip it.
我们跳过它吧。
For example, I now have a small Lin milk tea group
例如，我现在拥有一家规模较小的林氏奶茶集团，
with global business.
业务遍及全球。
I am now considering going public.
我现在正在考虑上市。
Where should I go?
我该去哪里？
There are three main choices in front of me:
我面前有三个主要选择：
A-shares, Hong Kong stocks and US stocks.
A股、香港股票和美国股票。
Today we will mainly talk about A-shares,
今天我们主要来谈谈A股，
but I will first briefly talk about the difference between
但首先我会简单谈谈
Hong Kong stocks and US stocks
香港股票和美国股票的区别
. In a nutshell, it is more market-oriented
。 简而言之，它更注重市场导向
, while A-shares will have more supervision
，而A股则会受到更多监管
and more audits.
和审计。
The reason behind this
造成这种情况的原因
is actually related to the characteristics of different markets.
其实与不同市场的特点有关。
You see, Hong Kong stocks Investors in Hong Kong and US stocks
你看，香港股票的投资者，以及美国股票的投资者，
are mainly professional institutions, with
主要是专业机构，他们拥有
stronger research capabilities and
更强的研究能力和
risk resistance.
风险承受能力。
Therefore, the exchange
因此，交易所
wants investors in the market
希望市场上的投资者
to screen the companies themselves.
自行筛选公司。
The exchange will
交易所只会对其进行
simply review them.
审核。
After a relatively procedural review,
经过相对常规的审查，
you can be listed if you don't have any major problems.
如果没有重大问题，你就可以被列入名单。
The listing conditions are
上市条件
also clearly written,
也写得很清楚，
mainly in terms of finance,
主要涉及财务方面，
such as
例如
your market value,
市值、
profit,
利润、
cash flow, etc.
现金流等。
For example, the Hong Kong main board,
例如，香港主板上市，
you only need to meet one of the three requirements.
你只需要满足三项要求中的一项即可。
example, in the
例如，在
past year, my income has exceeded 500 million Hong Kong dollars and my
过去一年里，我的收入超过5亿港元，我的
market value has exceeded 4 billion
市值超过40亿港元
. I have met the financial requirements for
。 我已经满足了
listing on the Hong Kong and US stocks.
在香港和美国证券交易所上市的财务要求。
It is actually not difficult
其实并不难
. The listing stage
。 上市阶段
depends on whether you can attract investors,
取决于你是否能吸引投资者，
that is, whether those professional institutions
也就是说，那些专业机构是否
are willing to buy your stocks.
愿意购买你的股票。
If you are not good enough and
如果你不够优秀，
no one is willing to buy your stocks,
没有人愿意购买你的股票，
then sorry,
那么很遗憾，
you have to delist.
你只能退市。 从
Logically,
逻辑上讲，
the US and Hong Kong stocks
美国和香港的股票都
belong to this kind of listing thresholds, which are relatively low,
属于这种上市门槛相对较低的类型，
and then let the market screen.
然后由市场进行筛选。
A-shares is that there
A股的特点是
are
散户投资者较多，
which is a bit more troublesome.
这会带来一些麻烦。
You see,
你看，
the professional screening ability of retail investors is not enough
散户投资者的专业筛选能力不够强
, it can even be said that it is quite insufficient
，甚至可以说相当不足
, and they may not look at financial data much.
，他们可能不太关注财务数据。
If your listing threshold is as low as that of US stocks,
如果你们的上市门槛像美国股票一样低，
many bad companies will be mixed in and listed together, and
很多不良公司就会混入其中一起上市，很
it is easy to fish in troubled waters and reap profits
容易在混乱的市场中捕鱼牟利
, which will seriously disrupt the market order.
，这将严重扰乱市场秩序。
Therefore, the China Securities Regulatory Commission
因此，中国证监会
hopes to have a good listing system.
希望建立一个良好的上市制度。
Some problematic companies can be screened out in one round
有些问题公司可以在一轮筛选中被剔除
. What will this lead to?
。 这将导致什么结果？
The listing review of A-shares,
A股的上市审核，
whether it is the China Securities Regulatory Commission or the exchange,
无论是中国证监会还是交易所，
whether you are on the main board or the Science and Technology Innovation Board
无论是主板还是科创板
, is much stricter
，
than that of Hong Kong stocks and US stocks.
都比香港股票和美国股票的审核严格得多。
In fact, A-shares also have clearly defined listing standards.
事实上，A股也有明确的上市标准。
For example, the Science and Technology Innovation Board
例如，科技创新委员会
requires a three-year revenue compound growth rate of more than 25%
要求三年营收复合增长率超过25%
or a recent revenue of more than 300 million yuan,
或近期营收超过3亿元人民币，以及
R&D expense requirements, etc.
研发费用等要求。这些规定
Isn't it written very clearly?
不是写得很清楚吗？
But I tell you
但我告诉你，仅仅
to just meet this
达到这个目标远远不够
. This is only the lowest threshold.
。 这只是最低门槛。
For example, the Science and Technology Innovation Board
例如，科创板
requires a net profit of no less than 50 million yuan in the last two years
要求近两年净利润不少于5000万元
, or a positive net profit in the most recent year
，或者最近一年净利润为正
and revenue of no less than 100 million yuan,
且营业收入不少于1亿元，
but in fact, if you look at those listed companies Most companies
但实际上，如果你看看那些上市公司，就会发现大多数公司
far exceed this indicator.
远远超过了这个指标。
You can see that Yingshi
你可以看到英仕
requires a positive net profit,
要求净利润为正，
but Yingshi's is 1 billion, and
但英仕的净利润是10亿，而
the requirement is that the revenue should not be less than 100 million
要求是收入不得少于1亿
. Yingshi's is 5.57 billion,
。 英仕的规模为 55.7 亿，比英仕
which is an order of magnitude higher.
高出一个数量级。
In fact, there were also those well-known
事实上，也有一些知名的
large companies that could not be listed
大公司由于研发投入不足而无法
on the Science and Technology Innovation Board
在科技创新板上市
due to insufficient R&D investment.
。
In short, what I want to say
总之，我想说的
is that Angela Chang has invisible wings.
是，Angela Chang 有一只看不见的翅膀。
A-shares have invisible thresholds that
A股存在一些不可见的门槛，这些门槛
are much higher
远
than the explicit thresholds specified on this website.
高于本网站上明确规定的门槛。
You have to pass this implicit threshold
您必须达到这个隐性门槛
to have a successful listing.
才能成功发布房源。
Then you say that it is so difficult to list on the A-share market,
既然你说在A股市场上市如此困难，
why do people still go for it?
为什么还有人要去尝试呢？
Why don't
为什么不去
you go to the Hong Kong and US
看看香港和美国的
stocks? Well, there are actually many reasons here.
股票呢？ 其实原因有很多。
One very direct reason
一个非常直接的原因
is that the trading volume of A-shares is much higher than that of Hong Kong stocks
是A股的交易量远高于香港股票
, so on average
，因此，
Generally speaking,
一般来说，A股的
it has a liquidity premium of 20% to 30% compared with Hong Kong stocks.
流动性溢价比香港股票高出20%至30%。
To put it bluntly, if
直白地说，如果
you list the same company on both A-shares and Hong Kong stocks,
同一家公司同时在A股和港股上市，
the valuation of A-shares is generally higher.
A股的估值通常会更高。
Of course, the high valuation of A-shares is not absolute.
当然，A股的高估值并非​​绝对。
For example, CATL, which was just listed on the Hong Kong stock market,
例如，刚刚在香港股市上市的宁德时代，由于其强劲的海外需求，其
a premium on Hong Kong stocks compared
在香港股票上的溢价可能高于在
with A-shares
A股上的溢价
because of its strong overseas demand.
。
The reason for the premium is that it has a greater business card effect.
之所以价格更高，是因为它具有更强的名片效应。
Everyone knows that it is difficult,
大家都知道这很难，
so it sounds very impressive
所以听起来很了不起
. You say that if you list on Nasdaq,
。 你说，如果一家公司在纳斯达克上市，
you may be a small company
它可能是一家小公司
, but if you list on A-shares,
；但如果一家公司在A股上市，
then the strength is unquestionable.
那么它的实力就毋庸置疑了。
You see, now some companies are valuable just by the shell.
你看，现在有些公司光凭空壳就很有价值了。
It is not only more impressive in words, but also more
它不仅用语言表达更令人印象深刻，而且也更贴近
real.
现实。
For example, Cooperation,
例如，作为一家A股上市公司，您在合作（
including financing and loans,
包括融资和贷款）方面
is generally easier
通常会更容易一些
for you as an A-share listed company.
。
Now let's take a quick look at
现在让我们快速了解一下
what the A-share listing has to go through.
A股上市需要经历哪些程序。
What are the invisible thresholds?
什么是那些看不见的阈值？
Generally, it will go through three stages.
一般来说，它会经历三个阶段。
The first is the application
第一个步骤是申请
, which is to prepare the materials for listing.
，即准备上市材料。
The core of this is the prospectus, which
其中最核心的部分是招股说明书，
is then submitted to the exchange.
然后将其提交给交易所。
The second step is review,
第二步是审核，
which is the exchange's review of the materials submitted by the company.
即 交易所对公司提交的材料进行审核。
If there are any problems,
如有任何问题，
you send the questions to the company for inquiry
您可以将问题发送给公司进行咨询
, and the company answers.
，公司会予以解答。
After these two rounds
经过这两轮审核后
, it
，该项目
will be submitted to the China Securities Regulatory Commission for registration,
将提交中国证监会进行注册，
and then the China Securities
之后中国
Regulatory Commission will review it again. Only after the China Securities Regulatory Commission passes it can you get a listing approval document.
证监会将再次对其进行审查。 只有经过中国证监会批准，才能获得上市许可文件。
So the review here is between the exchange and the China Securities Regulatory Commission.
所以，这里的审查是在交易所和中国证监会之间进行的。
These two rounds
这两轮债券
will finally enter the issuance stage.
最终将进入发行阶段。
That is pricing
这包括定价
, submitting
、提交
to the exchange, roadshows, etc., and
交易所上市、路演等等，
finally
最终
going public
上市
. Generally, when a company is considering going public,
。 一般来说，当一家公司考虑上市时，
it will invite a team of experts
它会邀请一个专家团队来
to help it evaluate where to go public,
帮助评估在哪里上市、
what the success rate of going public is, etc.
上市成功率是多少等等。
This team of experts
这个专家团队
mainly includes three
主要包括三家
investment banks, law firms, and accounting firms.
投资银行、律师事务所和会计师事务所。
The law firms and accountants are easy to understand. Lawyers
律师事务所和会计师事务所的语言都很容易理解。 律师
help
帮助
build some structures required for going public
构建上市所需的某些结构，
or dismantle some structures
或者拆除某些结构
. Accountants figure out financial accounting and auditing, and
。 会计师负责财务会计和审计，
more importantly, the investment bank
更重要的是，投资银行
is responsible for preparing the prospectus
负责准备招股说明书
and subsequent inquiries
和后续问询
, and helping to find investors, roadshows, etc., which
，并帮助寻找投资者、路演等，也
is selling stocks.
就是出售股票。
You see, they do the most work and
你看，他们工作量最大，
bear the greatest responsibility,
责任也最重，
so they usually get the most money.
所以他们通常得到的报酬也最多。
For example, this time, Yingshi
例如，这一次，应石
found CITIC Securities,
找到了中信证券、
CICC and Goldman Sachs , which
中金公司和高盛，这些
are all well-known investment banks for listings.
都是上市领域知名的投资银行。
They usually get How much money?
他们通常能拿到多少钱？
Law firms and accountants
律师事务所和会计师事务所
may get about 1% to 3% of the raised funds,
可能获得筹集资金的 1% 到 3%，
while investment banks may get 5%
而投资银行可能获得 5%
to 7 %.
到 7%。
Okay, our Xiao Lin Milk Tea Group is preparing to go public.
好的，我们小林奶茶集团正准备上市。
The next step is to submit materials
下一步是提交材料
and prepare this prospectus.
并准备这份招股说明书。
It is necessary to put in the company's business operations,
需要填写公司的业务运营、
legal structure, finances, and other information.
法律结构、财务状况及其他信息。
You have to put in
你必须填写
all the information you think the exchange or the Securities Regulatory Commission
你认为交易所或证券监管委员会
may need to know.
可能需要知道的所有信息。
Generally, it has to be at least several hundred pages.
一般来说，至少要几百页。
In fact, I feel that
事实上，我觉得
this prospectus is a bit like what?
这份招股说明书有点像什么？
It is a bit like you are going to write an argumentative essay.
这有点像你要写一篇议论文。
The title of this argumentative essay is
这篇议论文的题目是
to discuss why your company is suitable for A-share listing.
探讨贵公司为何适合在A股上市。
Please explain that your business is in line with the national strategy,
请说明贵公司的业务符合国家战略，
has good profitability,
具有良好的盈利能力，
and has controllable risks.
并且风险可控。
There are no problems with legal and financial matters.
法律和财务方面没有任何问题。
It is an absolutely honest and good company.
这是一家绝对诚信可靠的公司。
Write an argumentative essay.
请写一篇议论文。
The number of words should not be less than 100,000.
字数不应少于 10 万字。
I tell you that
我告诉你，
the prospectus
招股说明书里
literally discusses such a thing.
确实有提到这件事。 表面上看起来
It seems that there are no rules and regulations
似乎没有规章制度，
and it is very
非常
open ,
开放，
but in fact, it is very difficult. Imagine that I want to prove that a person has a problem,
但实际上却非常困难。 假设我想证明某人有问题，
I want to prove that he has accepted bribes
我想证明他收受了贿赂
, and I can find evidence of his bribery.
，而且我能找到他受贿的证据。
But if you want to prove that there is no problem with yourself, that
但如果你想证明自己没有问题，
I have not accepted bribes
没有收受贿赂
or made false statements, and that I am a good company,
或作虚假陈述，并且是一家好公司，
how do you prove it?
你该如何证明呢？
How do you prove it? You can only tell
如何证明这一点？ 你只有把
everyone all your income , all your consumption, deposits, equity structure,
你所有的收入、所有的消费、存款、股权结构
and everything you have done
以及你做的一切，都
from the bottom of
发自
your heart
内心地告诉大家，
, and then the exchange and the China Securities Regulatory Commission will feel your sincerity
交易所和中国证监会才能感受到你的诚意，
and see whether you are worthy of listing.
并判断你是否配得上上市。
The entire listing process,
整个挂牌过程，
including the subsequent inquiries
包括后续的询价
, is just pulling such a thing.
，都是为了达到这种目的。
Either the intermediary agency
中介机构
can get hundreds of millions of commissions for
可以通过
larger orders , but
更大的订单获得数亿佣金，但
ordinary people really can't do
普通人真的无法进行
this argumentation process
这种论证过程
, and there are many complicated issues here
，而且这里有很多复杂的问题
. How do they usually prove it?
。 他们通常如何证明这一点？
First of all,
首先，
you have to make it clear
你必须清楚地说明
what you do
你的
in terms of business, how you
业务内容、你的
make money, and how are you doing
盈利方式以及你
now? What will happen in the future? The
目前的经营状况？ 未来会发生什么？
key is what are you
关键在于，
going to do with the funds you raise when you go
你上市后打算如何使用筹集到的资金
public now ? It can definitely
？ 它未来肯定能为
bring business growth in the future.
企业带来增长。
I'm not doing it for money or cashing out.
我做这件事不是为了钱，也不是为了套现。
So this is why
所以，这就是为什么
it's difficult for the fast-moving consumer goods industry to be listed on the A-share market recently.
近年来快速消费品行业很难在A股市场上市的原因。
For example, this year, the milk tea stocks such as Bawang Cha Ji
例如，今年，像霸王茶记和混合冰城这样的奶茶股都
were all listed on the US and Hong Kong stock markets.
在美国和香港股市上市。
Although their businesses are also large
虽然他们的业务规模也很大，
and growing rapidly
而且发展迅速
, the problem is that your cash flow is sufficient. The problem is that your cash flow is sufficient and you
，但问题是你的现金流是足够的。 问题是你的现金流充足，你
have too much money .
钱太多了。
It's difficult for you to prove in the A-share market
你很难在A股市场证明
that I raised this money for business expansion
我筹集这笔资金是为了业务扩张
and not for money.
而不是为了赚钱。
So they simply won't approve it.
所以他们根本不会批准。 话虽
Well, having said that,
如此，
our milk tea group to be listed on the A-share market.
我们奶茶集团想要在A股市场上市还是有点困难的。
Hahaha.
哈哈哈。
Generally, the ones that are easy to pass are those that are used for
一般来说，容易通过的贷款是那些用于
financing purposes
融资目的的贷款
, either for research and
，无论是用于研发
development or for production.
还是生产。
It's relatively easy to explain some
解释一些
specific arguments.
具体论点相对容易。
For example, let's look at Yingshi.
例如，我们来看看英仕。
He wrote it quite clearly.
他写得很清楚。
First of all, he briefly explained how great
首先，他简要地解释了我有多么伟大
and excellent
和优秀
I am . He mainly makes panoramic cameras and sports cameras.
。 他主要生产全景相机和运动相机。
He listed all his product series,
他列举了他所有的产品系列，
such as the One X series, ACE series, Go series, etc.
例如 One X 系列、ACE 系列、Go 系列等等。这些产品
What are the features and
有哪些特点和
advantages?
优势？
Look , we have sold more than 5 billion in 24 years.
你看，我们在24年内已经卖出了超过50亿件产品。
What is the sales volume of each product line?
各产品线的销量是多少？
global coverage in China?
中国在全球的覆盖率占比是多少？
The United States and Europe each account for 23% .
美国和欧洲各占23%。
Look how wide the distribution
看看分布范围有多广
is . We are now the leader in panoramic cameras, with
。 我们目前是全景相机领域的领导者，
a market share of 70%
市场份额达 70%
. Well, we have actually talked about how Shadowstone
。 其实我们之前已经讨论过Shadowstone是如何
became the leader in panoramic cameras before
成为全景相机领域领导者的
. Friends who are interested can go and study archaeology.
。 有兴趣的朋友可以去学习考古学。
Well , now that you have become the leader,
既然你已经成为领导者，那么
what is the purpose of raising funds?
筹集资金的目的是什么呢？
Simply put,
简而言之，
it is to expand the business
就是为了拓展业务
. You see, it is said that
。 据说，
the business will be extended from panoramic cameras and sports cameras
该公司计划从2022年开始，将业务从全景相机和运动相机扩展
to the field of smart imaging starting from 2022.
到智能影像领域。
So it was stated in its prospectus that
因此，其招股说明书中提到，
I expect to raise 460 million yuan.
预计将融资4.6亿元人民币。
Of course, in the end, it actually raised 1.9 billion.
当然，最终它实际筹集到了 19 亿美元。 这
What will the 460 million be used for?
4.6亿将用于什么用途？ 其中
190 million will be used to build a production base
1.9亿将用于建设生产基地
and 270 million will be used in the R&D center.
，2.7亿将用于研发中心。
You see, part of it will be used for production
你看，其中一部分将用于生产，
and part of it will be used for R
一部分将用于
&D. Expanding the business is reasonable.
研发。 扩大业务规模是合理的。
In fact, if you look at the preference of A-shares,
事实上，如果你观察A股的偏好，就会发现
it will lead to a high
这将导致
industry concentration of listed companies.
上市公司的行业集中度很高。
I tell you,
我告诉你，
I have made a special statistics from 2019 to now. In the past five years,
我专门统计了从 2019 年至今的数据。 过去五年，
we have counted
我们统计了
all the companies that submitted applications for listing on the Shanghai Stock Exchange,
所有向上海证券交易所提交上市申请的公司，
not only those that were successfully listed,
不仅包括成功上市的公司，也包括
but also those that were not successful.
未成功的公司。
There are a total of 1,158 applications,
总共有 1158 个申请，
and 647 of them were successfully listed, like Yingshi, which is
其中 647 个成功上架，例如英仕，占比
about more than half.
超过一半。
If we classify them by industry,
如果按行业分类，
you will obviously find that
显然会发现
more than 2/3 of them are concentrated in these four categories.
超过三分之二的都集中在这四类中。
If you take a closer look,
仔细查看一下，
if your company happens to be in these four categories,
如果你的公司恰好属于这四类，
congratulations, you are one step closer to A-share listing.
恭喜你，你离A股上市又近了一步。
In short,
简而言之，
you see that these industries with more listings
您可以看到，这些上市企业较多的行业
either need funds for production,
要么需要资金用于生产，
such as professional equipment manufacturing, pharmaceutical manufacturing,
例如专业设备制造、制药、
computer communications, and other electronic equipment manufacturing, etc.,
计算机通信和其他电子设备制造等，
or they need funds
要么需要资金
for R&D,
用于研发，
such as software, information technology, services, etc.
例如软件、信息技术、服务等。
We just talked about industries. Let
我们刚才讨论的是行业。 让
me tell you
我告诉你，
that there is another major requirement for listing on
在A股市场上市还有另一个主要要求，
the A-share market, especially the Science and Technology Innovation Board.
特别是要在科技创新板上市。
Do you know what it is?
你知道那是什么吗？
It must comply with national strategies.
它必须符合国家战略。
You see, China has been vigorously promoting science and technology innovation, hard technology innovation,
你看， 中国一直在大力推进科技创新，尤其是硬科技创新，
and this is why
这就是为什么在
The success rate of listing on the Science and Technology Innovation Board is significantly higher than that on the main board.
科创板上市的成功率远高于在主板上市的成功率。
This is in line with the national strategy
这符合国家战略，
and it is not an unspoken rule.
而且并非不成文的规定。 上海证券交易所的规章制度
This is clearly written in
中对此有明确规定
the regulations of the Shanghai Stock Exchange.
。
You see, the Science and Technology Innovation Board should be oriented
你看，科技创新委员会应该
to the major needs of the country
面向国家的主要需求，
and mainly serve
主要服务于
enterprises that are in line with the national strategy.
符合国家战略的企业。
But you see,
但是，你看，
the name of this regulation is quite interesting.
这项法规的名称很有意思。
It is called the Interim Regulations.
它被称为临时条例。
If I want to change it one day,
如果有一天我想改，
I can change it at any time.
我可以随时改。
So if you want to be listed on the Science and Technology Innovation Board,
因此，如果你想被列入科学技术创新委员会名单，
you have to explain
你必须解释
how I am in line with the national strategy
我的工作如何符合国家战略，
and how I am in the direction of national policy support.
以及我的工作如何符合国家政策支持的方向。
You see, there is a very important part in
你看，英仕的招股说明书中有一个非常重要的部分
the prospectus of Yingshi ,
，
which is to explain that it
那就是解释它
meets the positioning of the Science and Technology Innovation Board . How does it meet
符合科技创新局的定位。 它如何满足
the requirements?
要求？
You see, it has panoramic technology, anti-shake technology,
你看，它拥有全景拍摄技术、防抖技术和
A I. Image processing technology.
人工智能图像处理技术。
There are many technologies.
技术种类繁多。
These are the underlying key technologies
这些是基础关键技术，
and are original and advanced.
均为原创且先进。
The company's core technologies
公司的核心技术
have been used in products,
已被应用于产品中，
and their influence is constantly increasing.
其影响力还在不断扩大。 将
The ability to transform core technological achievements
核心技术成果转化为实际应用的能力
is very outstanding. Don't you think it is in line with
非常出色。 你不觉得这符合
the national strategy? What is the national strategy?
国家战略吗？ 国家战略是什么？
The country's 14th Five-Year Plan clearly states that
该国的“十四五”规划明确指出，
promoting digital transformation,
推进数字化转型、
digital economy, key industries,
数字经济、重点产业、
virtual reality, and augmented reality
虚拟现实和增强现实
require these tools and industry solutions.
需要这些工具和行业解决方案。
Do you think Yingshi's argumentative paper is simple and clear?
你认为应诗的议论文简洁明了吗？
The country supports ABC
这个国家支持ABC
, and we happen to be doing ABC.
，而我们恰好也在做ABC。
And let me tell you,
而且我可以告诉你，
for those companies that are particularly in line with the national strategy,
对于那些特别符合国家战略的公司来说，
the approval can be very fast.
审批速度可能会非常快。
Look at the statistics I have collected.
看看我收集到的统计数据。
The average number of days for the Shanghai Stock Exchange
上海证券交易所接受申请的平均天数
to accept applications is about 300 days.
约为300天。
There is a company here that submitted its application on June 1, 2020,
这里有一家公司，2020年6月1日提交了申请，
and the China Securities Regulatory Commission issued an approval document on June 30.
中国证监会6月30日就签发了批准文件。
In less than a month, it was successfully registered and listed at
不到一个月的时间，就以光速成功注册上市
the speed of light. Let me
。 让我来
reveal the secret of
揭开
this company, which is SMIC.
这家公司——中芯国际——的秘密。
I won’t say much about
我不会过多赘述
why it conforms to the national strategy.
它为何符合国家战略。
since hard technology is easy to be listed,
既然硬技术很容易被列入专利清单，那么
is it possible for a company
一家公司是否有可能把
to package itself as hard technology,
自己包装成硬技术公司，
spend some money to buy some patents
花些钱买些专利
, say a few nice words
，说些漂亮话，然后大肆
to discuss
宣传一番呢
and fool around?
？
Well, that is very difficult
嗯，这非常困难
. The review in this area is very strict.
。 这个领域的审查非常严格。
It doesn’t mean that if you have a few patents,
这并不意味着拥有几项专利
you can prove that you are hard technology.
就能证明你拥有硬技术。
You have to prove whether the core results of your patented technology
你必须证明你的专利技术的核心成果是否
actually applied to your business, and
真正应用于你的业务，并且
the entire chain must be checked. The discussion must be very clear.
必须检查整个产业链。 讨论内容必须非常清晰。
For example, if you look at the prospectus of Innolux, you
例如，如果你查看群创光电的招股说明书，你就
can see what each patented technology is
可以看到每项专利技术是什么
. Was it developed by itself or purchased
。 它是自主研发的还是购买的
? Where
？
was it finally used? What stage
它最终在哪里被使用？ 它处于哪个阶段
is it in? Is it in R&D or mass production?
？ 目前处于研发阶段还是量产阶段？
You have to list them all very clearly.
你必须非常清楚地列出所有项目。
For example,
例如，
the first
第一项
panoramic image acquisition and stitching technology
全景图像采集和拼接技术
is that after the panoramic camera
是，全景相机
acquires 360-degree images,
采集 360 度图像后​​，
it must be stitched together through AI
必须通过人工智能将其拼接在一起
, so that
，从而
the fisheye effect that looks very interesting can be produced
产生看起来非常有趣的鱼眼效果
. There is also the invisible selfie stick, right?
。 还有隐形自拍杆呢，对吧？
The selfie stick is directly invisible,
自拍杆完全隐形，
and it is also achieved through AI stitching.
这也是通过人工智能拼接技术实现的。
, regardless of whether the auditors can understand them or not.
无论审计人员是否能够理解，这些技术都会被详细解释。
Anyway, I will give them to you first.
总之，我会先给你。
It is obvious that these technologies
很明显，
are indeed used in the products that he sells. The persuasiveness of the research and development
他销售的产品确实运用了这些技术。
in the product is very strong
该产品的研发说服力非常强
, and what's quite funny is that
，有趣的是，
you see, in the projects he is currently developing,
在他目前正在开发的项目中，
the responsibilities of each project
每个项目的责任都
must be implemented on specific people.
必须由特定的人来承担。
You can even know
你甚至可以知道
who is responsible for cloud computing,
谁负责云计算、
video editing, and panoramic security cameras,
视频编辑和全景安全摄像头，
and who is responsible for these. These
以及谁负责这些。 这些内容
are really revealed
确实毫无保留地全部揭露了出来
. Well, we just talked a lot
。 我们刚才讨论了很多
about what you want to prove
关于你想
at the business level
在商业层面证明什么
, how to write this argumentative paper, and
、如何撰写这篇论证性论文以及
what the reviewer looks at.
审稿人会关注哪些方面的内容。
In short, I am successful,
简而言之，我事业有成，
I have technology
拥有技术
, and I am good to the country.
，对国家有益。
In addition to business,
除了商业领域外，
there are two major areas
还有两个主要领域
, namely law and finance
，即法律和金融
, which are what lawyers and accountants do.
，这也是律师和会计师的工作内容。
This
这部分
is actually clearer than the business part
实际上比商业部分更容易理解
, and it needs to be broken down. I want to prove to everyone
，需要进一步分析。 我想向所有人证明
that I have no problem,
我没有问题，
but it is still quite troublesome to prove it in practice,
但在实践中证明这一点仍然相当麻烦，
especially
尤其是
in the financial aspect. First of all, the various details
在财务方面。 首先，
of the financial statements for the past three years
过去三年的财务报表各项细节
are certain
是确定的
, but you also have to explain in
，但你还需要对此进行补充说明
addition. For example, my business income is legitimate
。 例如，我的商业收入是合法的
, not that
，而不是
you sell this product at a high price to your second aunt's company,
你把这个产品以高价卖给你二姨的公司，
and you can make it as high as possible.
然后尽可能地抬高价格。
Who are your major customers and
你们的主要客户和
suppliers?
供应商有哪些？
You have to prove that there is no secret transfer of interests
你必须证明不存在秘密的利益转移
and no fraud
和欺诈行为
. All of them are real materials.
。 它们都是真实材料。 从
Then on the legal level, it is similar to
法律层面来说，
my structure being completely compliant.
我的结构完全符合规定。 贵
Who are your major shareholders
公司的主要股东有哪些？贵公司
you actually control?
实际控制多少股份？
All of these have to be pierced to the source layer by layer.
所有这些都需要一层一层地穿透到源层。
And what is very interesting is
非常有趣的是，
that I can't just list this information.
我不能简单地列出这些信息。
As long as you write it down
只要你把它写下来
and submit it,
并提交，
you They have to take responsibility.
他们就必须承担责任。
For each project, someone has to sign.
每个项目都需要有人签字。
For example, the investment bank's sponsor has to sign,
例如，投资银行的发起人必须签字，
and the lawyer has to sign, and the accountant
律师必须签字，会计师也
has to sign. If there is any problem,
必须签字。 如果出现任何问题，
your institution
您的机构
and the individual who signed will be held responsible .
和签字人将承担责任。
This is actually a key point of the registration system , which
这实际上是注册制度的一个关键点，
is to strengthen the responsibility of the intermediary institutions.
即加强中介机构的责任。
So why does the prospectus
那么，为什么招股说明书要
disclose the business and financial information so clearly
如此清晰地披露业务和财务信息呢
? In fact, it is also equivalent to
？ 事实上，这也相当于
a disclaimer of the intermediary institutions themselves
中介机构本身的免责声明
, which is that I did not hide anything for the company.
，即我没有为公司隐瞒任何事情。
I explained everything in detail.
我把所有事情都详细解释了一遍。
For example, you see, this is quite interesting.
例如，你看，这很有意思。
There is a special section in the prospectus
招股说明书中有一个专门的章节
called risk factors,
叫做风险因素，
which is about what risks the business may have.
介绍企业可能面临的风险。
It lists everything,
它列出了所有可能的风险，
for fear that there will be risks that I don't know. List them out.
因为我担心会有我不知道的风险。 列出来。
I may misjudge the future market trend,
我可能会误判未来的市场趋势，可能会
there will be a loss of technical talent,
出现技术人才流失、
product iteration that is not as good as expected,
产品迭代不如预期、
international trade friction,
国际贸易摩擦、
business downturn risk,
业务下滑风险、
exchange rate fluctuation risk,
汇率波动风险、
inventory management risk, etc.
库存管理风险等等。
Do you feel like a lot of it is nonsense?
你觉得其中很多都是无稽之谈吗？
It's like before you go to the exam room,
这就好比你进考场前
you say, "There is a risk that I can't do some questions, and there is a risk that
说：“我有可能不会做某些题，也有可能
I don't have enough time to answer
时间不够，
the questions and haven't filled in all the answer sheets
或者没填完所有的答题卡
. " Then you are really talking nonsense,
。” 这样说其实是胡扯，
but there is indeed this risk
但确实存在这种风险
, so you have to write it all down.
，所以你必须把所有事情都写下来。
Otherwise, if this risk becomes a reality in the end,
否则，如果这种风险最终成为现实，
it means that your intermediary agency's reminder is not in place
那就意味着你的中介机构的提醒没有到位
. Okay, all the things we just talked about
。 好了， 我们刚才讨论的所有事情都
are ready.
准备就绪了。 投资银行
After writing hundreds of pages of papers,
在撰写了数百页的文件后，
investment banks
通常会进行非常严格的内部审计流程，在
are officially submitted to the exchange.
正式提交给交易所之前，我们不会讨论这些流程。
This is the second stage,
这是第二阶段，
review and inquiry.
审查和调查。
You see, the prospectus
你看，招股说明书
is a bit like an argumentative paper.
有点像一篇议论文。
The review and inquiry process
审查和调查过程
is actually a bit like a paper defense,
实际上有点像论文答辩，
except that it is not face-to-face.
只不过不是面对面的。 此次
The exchange will have an organizing committee.
交流活动将设立组委会。
Generally, after receiving your paper,
一般来说，收到你的试卷后，
they will not directly say "
他们不会直接告诉你“
You passed or failed
你通过了还是没通过
". Usually, they will sort out some questions and send them to you
”。 通常情况下，他们会整理一些问题并发送给你
. Then you prepare for one or two months and submit it back
。 然后你准备一到两个月，再提交
for defense.
答辩。
You see,
你看，
this is one of the inquiry documents to Yingshi.
这是给英仕的其中一份询价文件。
For example, they asked
例如，他们会问
you whether the overall revenue growth rate during the reporting period was higher
你报告期内的整体收入增长率是否高于
than that of comparable companies in the same industry,
同行业可比公司，
and asked you to explain.
并要求你做出解释。
You see, your revenue is not good,
你看，你的收入不好，
your business is not good
你的生意不好
, and you are not
，而且你的
growing too fast.
增长速度也不够快。
They also have to ask
他们还需要问
me to make sure that you can explain clearly
我，以确保你能清楚地解释
that your revenue growth is real.
你的收入增长是真实的。
The rest is almost the same.
其余部分几乎相同。
It is probably in this form.
它很可能就是这种形式。
First, question one
首先，提出了第一个问题
was asked.
。
Please ask the issuer to blah blah blah 1234
请要求发行方进行 1234 项操作
, and then reply below
，然后在下方回复
, just like you should write an explanation before answering the question.
，就像你应该在回答问题之前写一个解释一样。
The answer was more than 20 pages long.
答案长达20多页。
Then question two was asked . Please
然后提出了第二个问题。 请
ask the issuer to supplement the omissions
要求发行人补充遗漏之处
.
。
The reply
回复
was probably like that.
大概就是这样。
Can you roughly feel
你能大致感受到
how detailed this question can be?
这个问题可以有多详细吗？
How detailed is it?
详细程度如何？
Let me give you an example.
我举个例子。
Before, a certain car company wanted to be listed on the A-share market.
此前，某汽车公司希望在A股市场上市。
This is a true story.
这是一个真实的故事。
In this inquiry stage,
在此调查阶段，
in order to verify the authenticity of its income,
为了核实其收入的真实性，
it was asked to provide
要求其提供
information on all major dealers and customers.
所有主要经销商和客户的信息。
You can imagine that the supply chain of
你可以想象，
such a large car company is complicated,
如此庞大的汽车公司的供应链非常复杂，
and the statistical difficulty of this is extremely high. Finally,
统计难度也极高。 最后，
coupled with some other reasons
由于其他一些原因
, a certain car company finally decided to go public on the Hong Kong stock market.
，某汽车公司最终决定在香港证券交易所上市。
Well, what is the approximate rate of
那么，
A-share applications that are finally approved
A股申请最终获批的比例大约是多少
? Hey, Data Xiao Lin is online again. Ha
？ 嘿，Data Xiao Lin 又上线了。 哈
, let's take all the data of the Shanghai Stock Exchange from 2019 to now.
，我们来看看上海证券交易所从2019年至今的所有数据。
I divide it by quarter . The
我把它分成四份。
blue one
蓝色部分
is
代表
the number of companies that were successfully approved for listing in this quarter
本季度成功获准上市的公司数量
. The red one is the number of companies that terminated their listing in this quarter.
。 红色部分代表本季度终止上市的公司数量。
Either they withdrew themselves
他们要么主动退出，
or they did not pass .
要么没通过。
This is roughly what I mean .
我的意思大致就是这样。
Please note
请注意，
that what I counted here is the time when the registration takes effect,
我在这里计算的是登记生效的时间，而
not the time when the bell was finally rung for listing,
不是最终敲响拍卖钟的时间，
so you can just take a rough look. You
所以您可以大致看一下。 您
can clearly see that
可以清楚地看到，
in the past two years The blue number
在过去的两年里，蓝色数字
is the number of companies that have been successfully approved for listing, which has decreased significantly.
代表成功获准上市的公司数量，这一数字大幅下降。  2020年第三季度，退市
It reached a peak of 55 companies
公司数量达到峰值55家。
In recent years,
近年来，
especially in 2023 and 2024,
尤其是在2023年和2024年，
the number of companies that have terminated their listings has suddenly increased.
退市公司的数量突然增加。
You can see that in the second quarter of 2024,
你可以看到，在 2024 年第二季度，令人
an astonishing 89 companies terminated their listings
震惊的是，有 89 家公司终止了上市
, and this time point
，而此时
happened to be the time when the new nine national policies were launched.
恰好是九项新的国家政策出台之时。
Hey, we will talk
嘿，我们
about the listing mechanism later. Ha,
稍后再讨论上架机制。 哈哈，
let me talk about it for a while.
让我来谈谈这件事。
Friends who have a little understanding of the capital market may have
对资本市场稍有了解的朋友可能
heard of
听说过
the approval system and
审批制度和
the registration system transformation. What
登记制度的转变。
we just discussed
我们刚才讨论的都是
is all about the current registration system
关于当前的注册系统
. But before 2019,
。 但在 2019 年之前，
A-shares actually adopted the approval system.
A 股实际上已经采用了审批制度。
Who approves it
谁批准的
? The CSRC.
？ 中国证监会。
All the company's materials must be submitted to the CSRC,
公司所有资料必须提交给中国证监会，
and then the CSRC will ask the company questions.
然后中国证监会将向公司提出问题。
It can be said that they have the power of life and death over whether you can be listed
可以说， 他们掌握着你是否能被列入名单的生死大权
. If you approve it, you go public. If
。 如果批准，就公开。
not, you go home.
否则，你就回家。
The whole process is not so transparent
整个过程不够透明
, which is obviously not conducive to the healthy development of the capital market.
，这显然不利于资本市场的健康发展。
So starting from about 2018 and 2019, A-shares also began
因此， 从 2018 年和 2019 年左右开始，A 股也开始像
like Hong Kong stocks and US stocks.
香港股票和美国股票一样向登记制过渡。
The registration system
注册系统
means that you submit your materials to the exchange for review.
意味着您需要将您的资料提交给交易所进行审核。
After the exchange has reviewed it,
交易所审核通过后，需将
you submit it to the CSRC for registration.
其提交给中国证监会进行注册。 中国
The CSRC is actually "approved". "But now
证监会实际上是“批准”的。  “但现在
in the actual operation,
实际操作中，
although A-shares are also called registration system
虽然A股也叫注册制
, compared with US stocks and Hong Kong stocks,
，但与美股和港股相比，
its substantive review is still required
其实质性审核仍然需要，
and is still very strict.
而且仍然非常严格。
But there is an obvious improvement, that
不过，也有一个明显的改进，那
is, it is more transparent.
就是更加透明了。
You see, we just saw so many documents and data .
你看，我们刚才看到了这么多文件和数据。
Every version of the materials submitted by the company,
公司提交的每一份材料，
the questions asked by the exchange,
交易所提出的所有问题，
including how the company answered,
包括公司的回答，
legal documents, audit documents, etc.,
法律文件、审计文件等等，都
are all public on the website of the Shanghai Stock Exchange.
在上海证券交易所的网站上公开。
I think from this perspective,
我认为从这个角度来看，
it is also an evolution of this mechanism
这也是该机制的演进
. Okay, let's go
。好，我们
back to the listing process. After
回到上市流程。
we submit the materials
提交材料后
and go through several rounds of inquiries and replies,
，经过几轮问询和回复，
if
如果
it passes the exchange smoothly, After the review by the Exchange and the CSRC,
顺利通过交易所审核，再经过交易所和证监会的审查，
if you get the approval from the CSRC,
如果获得证监会的批准，
then congratulations,
那么恭喜你，
you are now eligible for A-share listing.
你就具备了A股上市的资格。
Of course, this is not the end yet.
当然，这还没结束。
In fact, you still need to report to the exchange . You need
实际上，你还需要向交易所汇报，需要进行
a roadshow, and
路演，
you also need to talk to investors from large institutions to
还需要与投资者沟通。” 大型机构会来
see what the market's investment intentions are,
了解市场的投资意向，以及
what the appropriate pricing should be, etc.
合适的定价策略等等。
Let me tell you
我得说，
that roadshows and pricing are
路演和定价都是
very complicated things, so
非常复杂的事情，所以今天
we won't go into
我们就不深入
details today. Anyway, after you have finished all this,
探讨了 。总之，等你完成这些之后，
you can go public.
就可以上市了。Instone
Instone's issue price is 47 yuan,
的发行价是47元，
and it raised a total of 1.9 billion yuan
总共募集了19亿元
. Think about it,
。想想看，
there are few A-share IPOs
A股IPO本来就少
, and Instone is a hard technology company. The market demand for leading enterprises
，Instone又是一家硬科技公司，市场对龙头企业的需求
is also very strong. The
也非常强劲，
stock price rose by 285% at the opening.
开盘股价就涨了285%。
Look, the investors are happy.
你看，投资者们都高兴坏了，
The whole place is full of people holding panoramic cameras.
现场到处都是 拿着全景相机的人。
In fact, one investor said
其实，一位投资者说
that he always dealt with some old money before,
他以前接触的都是一些老钱，
but he saw the vitality of technology
但这次在
in the so-called new money like JK
像JK这样的新钱身上看到了科技的活力
. How do you feel today?
。你今天感觉如何？哈哈，
I was very calm before I met you
见到你之前我还挺平静的
, hahaha.
。
As a post-90s person in the Science and Technology Innovation Board, are you the first person?
作为90后进科创板的人，你是第一个？
If
要说
weight is counted, it counts. Hahaha.
分量 ，那可就分量了。 哈哈。
If weight is counted, it counts. Hahaha. Do you have any special feelings?
如果重量算进去，那就算数。哈哈。 你有什么特别的感受吗？
I am very lucky
我很幸运，我们
that a group of college students who are tinkering with their hands have received
这群大学生靠着动手做东西，得到了
support from many people. We
很多人的支持。我们
have received
得到了
support from many people.
很多人的支持。
During the entire listing process,
在整个上市过程中，
we have received a lot of support and care from the society and regulators.
我们得到了社会和监管机构的大力支持和关心。
After all, our company started a business
毕竟，我们公司
without working before .
之前没有任何工作经验，一
Many things were not so perfect at the beginning
开始很多事情都不尽如人意
, but we still received a lot of tolerance
，但我们仍然得到了很多包容
. I am
。我
too humble
太谦虚了
. What is the most difficult thing about listing?
。上市最难的是什么？
It still puts higher requirements
它对公司治理结构提出了更高的要求
. Because we used to only care
。因为我们以前只关注
about the business,
业务，
but we found that if there is only business but
但我们发现，如果只有业务而
no good corporate governance structure
没有良好的公司治理结构
,
，不仅
it will not only be difficult to become a qualified public company,
很难
but also difficult to become a qualified public company.
成为一家合格的上市公司，而且
It may also be difficult to support the company to go further.
可能也很难支撑公司继续发展。
This is something
这一点
we realized very late,
我们醒悟得比较晚，
yes, but it also made up for a lot of lessons. Come on,
但也让我们吸取了很多教训。加油，
come on, congratulations,
加油 恭喜
congratulations,
恭喜，
JK, you can,
JK，你可以，
on, thank you, thank you, congratulations, congratulations, thank you, no, no thank you, come on, thank you, thank you, thank you. In fact, that day, the entire listing
来吧，谢谢，谢谢，恭喜恭喜，谢谢，不，不，谢谢，来吧，谢谢，谢谢，谢谢。事实上，那天整个上市
process
过程
was
只用了
ten
十分钟
to twenty
到 二十
minutes. Mainly
分钟。 大部分时间
, everyone came up to
，大家都在上来
take various photos and group photos for more than an hour.
拍照和合影，持续了一个多小时。
Various investors took turns to come up and take photos with JK.
各个投资者轮流上来和JK合影。JK
JK stood there like a mascot,
像吉祥物一样站在那里，
and as these investors,
作为这些投资者，
it is natural for them to be happy, right
他们高兴也是人之常情，对吧
? They successfully invested in the first post-90s boss
？他们成功投资了首位在
to be listed on
科创板上市的90后老板。
This is a definite success story.
这绝对是一个成功的案例。
In fact, in China,
事实上，过去两年，中国
the overall attitude towards the capital market
对资本市场的整体态度
has changed in the past two years
发生了变化
. Earlier, it was mainly The goal is to
。以前，主要目标是
grow bigger and stronger.
做大做强。
Later, the number of listed companies gradually increased
后来，上市公司数量逐渐增加到
to more than 5,000.
5000多家。
Basically, the leaders of various industries
基本上，各行业的领军企业
have all been listed.
都上市了。
So last year, the new "Nine National Regulations" were introduced
所以去年，出现了新的“九大国企”。 新的“九项国家规定”出台
, which is equivalent to a guiding document for the capital market.
，相当于资本市场的指导性文件。
It wants to shift from increasing scale to improving quality.
其目的是从扩大规模转向提高质量。
Those with good profitability should pay dividends, and
盈利能力强的公司应该派发股息，
those with poor profitability should be delisted.
盈利能力差的公司应该退市。
Another
另一个
purpose is to screen out the good and healthy companies that remain.
目的是筛选出优质健康的公司。
At the same time, your company cannot just make money by itself,
同时，公司不能只顾自身盈利，还要
pay dividends and return this profit to investors
派发股息，将利润回馈给投资者
and society.
和社会。
So after the new "Nine National Regulations" came out,
因此，新的“九项国家规定”出台后，
the supervision in this regard will be stricter.
这方面的监管将更加严格。
This is why we just said
这就是我们刚才说的
that the red is so high.
红色区域如此之高的原因。
These are
这些都是
behind the A-share listing. Finally, congratulations to Insta360 on its successful listing
A股上市背后需要经历的9981层考验。最后，祝贺Insta360成功上市
. Thank you for supporting this video, which
。感谢大家支持本视频，
allows everyone to understand the doorway behind the listing.
让大家了解上市背后的故事。